[music]
>> Hello. My name is Thomas and I'm joined
here today with my colleague Thaddeus.
We are part of the team that works on
the set of developer tools and we'll be
showing you the latest set of testing
capabilities added in this release.
In this release, we have added
the ability to run tests in Visual
Studio Code.
You'll be able to see all of your tests
in the testing explorer
and see which one have failed and passed
and get a great overview of what you
have in there.
Part of this is a set of run profiles.
There is the profile for publishing and
running your tests. That means that you
will publish your package and run the
tests all in one operation. Or you can
decide just to run your tests.
Next up, you can debug all of your tests
and lastly, you can decide to run your
test and collect code coverage
information.
All of this is done without any specific
application added to your system, but
only using the parts part of the
platform.
But let's show you how it's done
in the product.
In here, we have a workspace with two
projects. I have my core set of
functionality and I have a project with
all of my tests.
With the new release, we now have the
testing panel over here.
This will show me all of my tests first
grouped by my project, then by code
units, and lastly, it will show all of
the tests in here.
At the top, we will see the run
profiles. Up here, we have the publish
and run.
We have the ability to debug our tests
and to run the test with code coverage
information.
Let's try and run the test with code
coverage information.
>> [snorts]
>> So, I'll take and select my project and
I'll run with code coverage information.
And you can see in just a few seconds,
we have
a set of results here.
Some of them have passed, some of them
have failed. So, let's dig into this.
Since I ran all my tests with code
coverage information, it will give me
this new code lens element.
It tells me that I have four tests that
have executed this procedure and one of
them has passed.
If I click on the code lens element, it
will now run the associated set of
tests.
I can see down here in the test results
that I have three tests that have failed
and one has passed.
>> [snorts]
>> But now, let's figure out what's the
what has gone wrong here. I'll hand it
over to my colleague to figure out
what's wrong. Thank you, Thomas. So, now
as we have seen, we have a whole bunch
of tests failing. And traditionally, how
we would figure out what's failing and
try to fix it is that we would debug
this test.
And if you use the AL test tool, like
the old way of running tests in the
client, you'll know that actually
debugging AL tests
can be a big pain. Like you have to sort
of like attach your debugger to it, find
the right session, and then execute the
test. Um but now, from VS Code, it's
like really, really easy to set up a run
and debug. So, there's a couple of
different ways you can do this. The
first way is from the test explorer
itself.
You have this little thing here that you
can say debug test.
Uh you can also go to a specific test
and in the sidebar, you have this icon.
You can right click debug test.
But
for me personally, my favorite way of
running tests, especially when they're
failing,
is to run it from the test results here
because you have this nice little thing
here that says, "Hey, debug failed
test." So, let's do that.
And what this will do is that it will
actually set up the debugging session
for you
and it will run the test and then
from that point onwards, it should be
the same
as any other debug session. So, as you
can see, it's actually attached. We're
already in debug mode.
And from this point on, it's the same as
every other debug session. You can step
over, you can step in, you can step out.
You can see the value of variables.
It's the same as any other debugging
session.
Um so, I could use this to
figure out why the test is failing.
Um but you know, I'm a bit lazy and I
don't want to.
But I have a really, really good new
coworker called Copilot who's excellent
at fixing failing tests.
So, the good thing about having
integrated with the VS Code tools is
that we get the ability for agents to
run tests out of the box. Uh to set this
up, you'll need to
make sure that the run test tool is
enabled over here.
Um
and you can see that it's actually done
that already. It's actually run the
test. It's found that eight um seven of
these are failing. It's going to try to
fix it. So, while this is going on, I'm
going to talk a bit more about how all
of this is implemented behind the
scenes.
Now,
the test running framework in the
platform uses the configuration in your
launch.json. So, this means if you're
targeting multiple sandbox instances or
if you have multiple on-prem instances,
you can target different servers with
your launch.json.
This also means if you have different
companies that you use to manage your
test data, you can select which company
the test runs under using the startup
company property in the launch.json.
The big one for you to be aware of is
that we are not using AL test runners.
This means that we currently do not have
any support for running AI or
data-driven test suites.
And if you do have test code units that
rely on functionality that's provided by
a test runner, especially for setup and
teardown events, uh these may not work.
Finally, when it comes to test
isolation. So, traditionally, test
isolation is provided by the test
runner,
but because we don't have a test runner
here, we actually configure this
dynamically based on the required test
isolation property that's set on the
test code unit. And if you do not have
this set, it will default to code unit
level isolation.
And for those of you who are using a
third-party tool for running AL tests
already and you find that this conflicts
with your existing workflow, you can
disable the test integration in VS Code
using the AL disable test running
setting.
So, let's go back to VS Code to see how
our agent is going. Oh, it's good. So,
you can see that it's actually found the
bug. It's actually fixed it here and
it's done a second test run to validate
that its fix was correct. And in
general, with agentic development, I
find this to be very powerful. The
giving the agent the ability to run and
validate its own AL test own AL code
using tests um
significantly improves the accuracy of
the agentic development.
Uh before I go, I do have a few last
things that I want to tell you.
Um the first one is that we have a bunch
of other videos on BCAL that you should
definitely check out. The first one is
we have the what's new in AL.
Um and this is a session that covers all
the other improvements we've done in the
VS Code extension for AL. So, we've It's
not just test running that we've
improved. We've added a whole bunch of
other features, including some other
agentic tools that your agent can use as
well.
The other one you should definitely
check out is we have a session on AI
test. So, if you're interested into
seeing how we in Microsoft test our AI
features or how you can leverage that
for your own testing or even if you're
just interested in data-driven testing,
um check out that session as well.
And finally, uh we will have a bit on
the AL MCP. And this is a tool for those
of you who are not using VS Code,
but have moved on to other agentic tools
such as GitHub Copilot key
or Cloud Code or maybe you're running
this in a pipeline and you're not using
VS Code, but you still want to access
all of these additional tools so that
your agents are more effective.
Well, check out that session on how your
agents can also get access to these
tools there.
And last but not least, I want to say
thank you to all of you. I hope you all
have
greater productivity using these tools
and I will see you next time. Thank you
very much.